Guide to the New-York Historical Society Public Relations Material circa 1939-2006 NYHS-RG 8
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society public relations material
circa 1939-2006
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 8
8.75 Linear feet in 14 boxes of various sizes. + 1 oversize folder
The New-York Historical Society public relations material record group contains press releases and press kits produced by N-YHS's Public Relations Department primarily between 1941 and the 1990s, with some subsequent material. The materials principally hold descriptive information about exhibitions, film series, and other programs presented by N-YHS. The releases also include publicity about organizational matters, such as new collection acquisitions, fundraising initiatives, and the like.
Biographical/Historical Note
From its founding in 1804, N-YHS has publicized its institutional objectives, programs, galleries and exhibitions, publications, fundraising needs, and other matters. Indeed, N-YHS printed a public announcement of its mission in February 1805, just three months after its inaugural meeting. Printed appeals, newspaper advertisements, and other materials were produced throughout the nineteenth century and into the twentieth. Publicity took on a special focus beginning about 1939 as N-YHS began to expand its programs and the professional staff to support them. The increased programming and staffing at that time was principally the result of the receipt of a substantial bequest from the Mary Gardiner Thompson estate. This bequest was used, in part, to complete the expansion of the Central Park West building and to fund the growth in staff size. Part of this growth was directed toward greater publicity about N-YHS's varied programs and for much of the following decades the Public Relations Department also held responsibility for conducting tours, school visits, film series, and other programs.
Among N-YHS's publicity initiatives was increased outreach to the press, and this record group focuses on the press releases and, later, press kits that were produced. The first supervisor of these publicity initiatives was Alexander J. Wall, Jr., son of N-YHS's then-director. Wall Jr. left the position to serve in the military during World War II, returning in 1945. While he was away, the work was continued by others, including Dorothy Barck and Richard Baker, editors of N-YHS's publications. Wall Jr. left N-YHS about 1950 and Meryle Evans took the publicity position for about six years. Evans was succeeded by Susan McMahon in 1957, George Sykes in 1960, Richard Cunliffe in 1963, and Lawrence Skutch in 1968. After Skutch's departure about 1972 through the end of the date range of this record group in the early 2000s, various individuals appear as contacts on press releases and in the files including Joyce Crawford (circa 1976-1979), Edith Sakell (circa 1979-1983), Gail Rentsch (circa 1983-1986), Nancy Donner (circa 1986-1992), Jennifer Carlson (1990s), and Stewart Desmond (from the mid-1990s to early 2000s).
(Principal sources for the above were R.W.G. Vail's Knickerbocker Birthday, N-YHS's Annual Reports, and the press releases.)
Scope and Contents Note
This record group contains press releases and press kits produced by the New-York Historical Society's Public Relations Department between 1941 and 1993, and various public relations and administrative files, especially for the 1980s-1990s, with some subsequent material to 2006. The releases contain information about recent acquisitions, staff appointments, the N-YHS's mission and collecting policy, current exhibitions, children's programs, lectures, film and concert series, and other events at the institution. Press kits were folders of press releases and other documents with facts about N-YHS exhibitions, such as brief historical context and dates, and other events.
Arrangement Note
The record group is organized in four series:
Series I. Press Releases, circa 1939-2006
Series II. Press Kits, 1976-1995
Series III. Compiled Public Relations Files, 1950s, 1970s-2002
Series IV. Stewart Desmond Files, 1995-2001
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society public relations material (NYHS-RG 8) are as follows:
Over the course of its history, N-YHS produced a variety of documents publicizing its programs and operations. Many of these brochures, fliers, posters, calendars, and other matter can be found in the New-York Historical Society ephemera record group (NYHS-RG 14).
For a perspective on the press coverage N-YHS received in the New York and national press, especially from 1870 and into the late twentieth century, see the New-York Historical Society press clippings record group (NYHS-RG 7).
Arts publicity -- New York (State) -- New York.; Education.; Exhibitions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Learned institutions and societies -- Public relations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Libraries and institutions -- Public relations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Museums -- Educational aspects -- New York (State) -- New York.; Publicity; Press kits.; Press releases.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.; New-York Historical Society -- Public relations.
- Series I. Press Releases, circa 1939-2006; 2.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series includes press releases distributed by N-YHS to various publications from 1941-1993, primarily publicizing the institution's public events, such as exhibitions, lectures, film series, school programs, and walking tours. These materials include fact sheets, schedules and calendars of events, checklists, exhibition contributor biographies, brochures, and other background information. This information often includes historical and other context related to the publicized program; examples include a "Sampler of Ballroom Etiquette" from a 1988 exhibition. The series includes a small amount of material from prior to 1941 and after 1993.
  Press releases also concern N-YHS organizational matters, such as new collection acquisitions, changes in senior management positions, the establishment of a new conservation program, and fundraising initiatives, such as the announcement for N-YHS's first ever major fundraising gala in 1988. The final press releases of the series, from 1993, concern N-YHS's efforts to resolve its financial troubles.
  Particularly for the 1980s-1990s, the files include so-called "press round-ups." These were summaries compiled by N-YHS of the coverage in the press of N-YHS exhibitions and other events.
  Arrangement Note
  This series is arranged chronologically. The bulk of the releases appear to have come from the original files of the Public Relations Department, but these have been filled out with additional copies by releases found by the archivists in the files of other departments.
  - Press Releases (17 folders), circa 1939-1958 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-17)
    The first folder includes a list, possibly incomplete, of press releases from 1955-1960. The 1958 folder includes a checklist of objects from the Stuyvesant Family Portraits exhibition.
  - Press Releases (20 folders), 1959-1975 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-20)
    The 1959 folder includes the checklists for The Hudson, River of History, from Lake Champlain to the Sea, 1609-1959 and Rediscovered Painters of Upstate New York, 1700-1875 exhibitions. There are two lists of releases: one for 1968 through 1973, the other for 1974-1979.
  - Press Releases (13 folders), 1975-1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-13)
    The 1980 folder includes the checklist for the exhibition Tiffany Silver. The 1981 folder includes a Report of the Museum Committee concerning the acquisition of Portrait of Philip Hone (1780-1851) by Rembrandt Peale (1778-1860). The 1982 folder includes the press release for A Collector's Sampler: Library Accessions 1980-1982, which includes significant library gifts and purchases of the prior two years. The 1983 folder includes the location plan for paintings in the North Gallery of the 4th floor.
  - Press Releases (9 folders), 1984-1988 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-9)
    The 1984 (July-Dec.) folder includes a list of Presidential and Vice-Presidential candidates between 1789-1984 and the winner of the election. The 1986 (July-Dec.) folder includes a "Sampler of Ballroom Etiquette" to accompany the press release for The Pleasure of Your Company: Parties and Balls in NYC exhibition. The 1987 (Jan-June) folder includes materials on a series of walking tours organized through N-YHS to notable neighborhoods including Astor Place and Gramercy Park.
  - Press Releases (8 folders), 1988-1991 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-8)
    The 1988 (Jan.-June) folder includes the release for the film series "Murder, Mystery, and Mayhem: Crime Films at the New-York Historical Society." Descriptions of each film are included as well as descriptions of the original newsreels that preceded each film presented. The 1988 (July-Dec.) folder includes the press release regarding N-YHS's first-ever Fundraising Gala, held October 31, 1988. Major celebrities and dignitaries such as George Plimpton, Mayor Ed Koch, and Mary Tyler Moore were guests.
  - Press Releases (13 folders), 1991-2006 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-13)
    Includes the 1994 press release from the New York State Attorney General announcing the conditions under which the office agreed that N-YHS could sell (deaccession) collection items. Includes the 1995 press release from Town & Country concerning the display of a previously unseen Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis portrait at N-YHS (with photograph and related issue of Town & Country), as well as the releases related to the exhibitions marking the re-opening of N-YHS's galleries in 1995. Press releases after 1993 are spotty and are often print-outs of announcements from N-YHS's Internet website.
- Series II. Press Kits, 1976-1995; 1.25 Linear feet
  This series includes press kits on exhibitions produced by the New-York Historical Society dating between 1976 and 1994. The press kits typically contain press releases and fact sheets, with basic information such as names of contacts, sponsors, and curators, opening events, and a brief historical background of the subject. Many kits include additional documents, such as programs, checklists, brochures, and photographs concerning each exhibition. The exhibitions were an eclectic mix of themes, ranging from the portrayal of domestic life in 19th century America to exhibitions of the work of artists and photographers to the opening of the N-YHS conservation lab.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - The Dutch Republic in the Days of John Adams, 1976 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
  - Remember the Ladies: Women in America, 1977 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
    Abigail Adams is one of many women celebrated in this exhibition. Includes photo and biography of historian Linda Grant DePauw, consultant for the exhibition.
  - Small Folk: A Celebration of Childhood in America, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
    A comprehensive view of American childhood from the 17th-19th centuries.
  - Artists and Architects Collaboration, 1981 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    Explores the history and future collaboration between artists and architects. Includes booklet on works and architects involved.
  - Oom Pah Pah: The Great American Band, 1982 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
  - Birth of New York: Nieuw Amsterdam 1621-1664, 1982 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
  - The World of Tiffany: The Egon Neustadt Collection of Tiffany Lamps., 1983 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
    This gift collection from Dr. Egon Neustadt represents pieces from each of Tiffany's major periods.
  - Firefighting on Parade: 1700 to 1865, 1983-1984 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
    Traced the history of firefighting in America from Colonial times to the Civil War. Includes The New York Fire House Fact Sheet.
  - Lights, Camera, Action! New York's Silent Film Studios, 1983-1984 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
    Featured photographs, including of stars such as Marion Davies, Gloria Swanson, Rudolph Valentino, and W.C. Fields, posters, and artifacts from the Astoria Motion Picture and Television Foundation and other museums. Folder includes a newsletter of the Astoria Foundation.
  - Lost in the Shuffle: Playing Cards and Board Games from Bygone Days, 1984 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10)
    Materials of nearly 100 rare European and American playing card decks and board games from the 16th to the 20th centuries.
  - New York and the China Trade, 1984 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
    Traces the history of the China trade chronologically and its contribution to the decorative arts to celebrate the 200th anniversary of the sailing of the ship Empress of China. Includes a list of distinguished exhibition committee members.
  - A Pageant of Heraldry in Britain and America., 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    Commemorated the quincentennial of the incorporation of the College of Arms by King Richard III in 1484. It was the first major heraldic exhibition of its kind to be mounted in the United States.
  - The Lawrence Scripps Wilkinson Collection of Toys, 1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
    Focused on the manufacturing period from the beginning of the Industrial Revolution to the 20th century.
  - Visions of Liberty, 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
    Photographs relating to the Statue of Liberty to celebrate the centennial of the statue. Approximately 75 original photographs from the 1870s to the present were assembled for the exhibition, which was divided into three sections: Bartholdi's Vision, "...To Breathe Free," and "Liberty Enlightening the World."
  - Centuries of Childhood in New York: 275th Anniversary of the Trinity School, 1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
    Focused on the changing image of children in New York from 1709 to 1984. Also celebrated the 275th anniversary of the Trinity School, the oldest continually operated school in New York City.
  - Audubon's Birds of North America: The Original Watercolors, 1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 16)
    Celebrated the bicentennial of the birth of John James Audubon. All of Audubon's 433 known original watercolors painted for his monumental volume, The Birds of America. Also includes a release for the exhibition John James Audubon: Science into Art at the American Museum of Natural History, which coincided with the N-YHS exhibition.
  - Niagara: Two Centuries of Changing Attitudes, 1986 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 17)
  - Jackie Robinson: An American Journey, 1987 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
  - N-YHS Walking Tours, 1987 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
    New-York Walks explored the history and development of New York's varied neighborhoods. Includes a brochure of the program and maps of the various walking tours.
  - Student Tours, 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
    N-YHS tours offered to students from grade K-High School. Included are descriptions of tours appropriate for each grade level.
  - Government by Choice: Inventing the United States Constitution, 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
    Major exhibition, lecture series, catalogue, workshops, and tours as part of the Celebration of the 200th Anniversary of the US Constitution. Includes photos of artifacts on display and a small copy of the Constitution published by the N-YHS.
  - Jasper F. Cropsey: Artist and Architect, 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
    Featured 75 paintings and drawings by Cropsey (1823-1900), 19th century American landscape artist.
  - Artistic Houses: Lavish Interiors of Nineteenth-Century New York, 1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
    Illustrated the manner in which upper class New Yorkers of the 19th century lived, highlighting figures such as William H. Vanderbilt and the Astors.
  - Francis W. Edmonds: American Master in the Dutch Tradition, 1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7)
    Focused on the work of Francis W. Edmonds (1806-1863), and the stylistic debt 19th century American art owed to Dutch paintings. Included 27 paintings, 13 oil studies and drawings, sketchbooks, and 3 engravings.
  - Arnold Newman: Five Decades, 1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 8)
    Traveling retrospective of Newman's work in honor of his 50th anniversary as a photographer. Included were 150 predominately black and white images featuring portraits of many influential personalities of the 20th century.
  - Thanksgiving Harvest: Food and Wine Festival 1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
    N-YHS celebrated Farm-City Week by promoting ten restaurants and NY state wineries. Organizations provided information on how each group's agricultural /horticultural programs were interspersed throughout the metropolitan area. Included are the pamphlets on the food and wine festival and The Virtuosi Quintet, which provided music for the event.
  - Bellows, Bobbins, and Butter Churns: Keepings House in Nineteenth-Century America, 1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10)
    This exhibition provided an in-depth look at what domestic life was like in rural working-class America in the 19th century. The exhibition was divided into several sections such as tending the hearth, cooking and baking, and food service.
  - The Rise and Fall of New York: Building and Unbuilding Manhattan, 1988 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 11)
    Exhibition on architectural drawings, photographs, and prints exploring the changes in the urban landscape of New York City from the mid-19th to mid-20th centuries. Highlights included the Woolworth Building, the Crystal Palace, and the second Madison Square Garden built in 1890.
  - Celebrating the Holidays in Old New York, 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 12)
    The spirit of New York was captured in this presentation of 19th century photographs and other materials, such as Washington Irving's Knickerbocker's History of New York (1809).
  - Hard Cider and Hot Air: The Selling of the President, 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 13)
    Presidential campaign ephemera captured 150 years of presidential salesmanship. Included were eclectic examples of campaign rhetoric and marketing tactics of political parties such as the Free-Soil party and the Bull Moose (Progressive) party.
  - Opening of Book and Paper Conservation Lab, 1989 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 14)
    Included are pamphlets and photos announcing the new conservation lab, and a 1988 NY Times article on N-YHS's efforts to raise funding for its future.
  - Cased Images: The 150th Anniversary of Photography, 1989 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 15)
    Celebrated the invention of photography with an exhibition of over 40 unique daguerreotypes dating from 1840-1860 from the N-YHS collections. Also included is a leaflet announcing a lecture on The Modern Daguerreotype.
  - Encyclopedia of New York City, circa 1989 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 16)
  - Irving Browning: City of Contrasts, 1989 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
    Focused on the changing urban architecture, lifestyle, and people of New York in the 1920s and 1930s. On display were 80 photographs by Browning (1895-1961) that documented both the glamorous and destitute environment that existed in the city at that time.
  - An American Sampler: Folk Art from the Shelburne Museum, 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
    Included more than 120 works from the Shelburne Museum's extensive Americana collection, including quilts, coverlets, rugs, weathervanes, and carved figures.
  - Luman Reed Gallery 1830s Permanent Installation of American and European Art, 1990 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3)
  - Why History?: Keynote Address and Panel Discussions, 1990 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
    Explored the pivotal role of history's influence on American culture in a three-part multi-disciplinary program.
  - Below the Line: Living Poor in America, 1990 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
    A display of Eugene Richards' black and white photos.
  - ART what though EAT: Images of Food in American Art, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
  - N-YHS Programs and Exhibitions, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7)
    Includes material on the following: Luman Reed Gallery, Thomas Jefferson Bryan Gallery, Audubon's Birds of America, and general N-YHS program brochures.
  - McKim, Mead and White's New York: Turn-of-the-Century Architectural Drawings and Photographs, 1991 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
  - The Thomas Jefferson Bryan Gallery: Changing Attributions, 1990 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 9)
    Includes photographs of some of the paintings.
  - The Taste of Andrew Carnegie, 1991 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10)
  - Imagining the New World: Columbian Iconography, 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11)
    Marked the Quincentenary of Christopher Columbus' voyage to the Americas in 1492.
  - While They Fought: The Home Front in New York City, 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 12)
    Commemorated the 50th anniversary of the U.S. entry into World War II.
  - Building City Hall: Competition, Construction, and Context, 1992 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13)
    Featured 47 architectural drawings, as well as watercolors, prints, and manuscripts. Includes a list of architectural collections held by N-YHS as of 1994.
  - The Equitable Gallery: 19th Century American Masterworks, 1994 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 14)
    Exhibition at The Equitable Gallery of 50 American paintings and sculpture from N-YHS's collection.
  - Thomas Cole: Landscape into History, 1994 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 15)
    Retrospective of works by Cole (1801-1848), an early 19th century landscape painter.
  - Treasury of the Past, 1995 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 16)
    Exhibition celebrating the May 1995 re-opening of the N-YHS galleries after being closed for two years; includes object photographs and checklist. Also includes Executive Director Betsy Gotbaum's Vision Statement released in conjunction with the re-opening. The checklist for the exhibition On the Avenue, Fifth Avenue that also opened then is included in the packet.
- Series III. Compiled Public Relations Files, 1950s, 1970s-2002; 3 Linear feet in 3 record cartons + 1 oversize folder
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes files primarily concerning exhibitions, development of the Luce Center, and other programs, with some files related to general public relations activities and notes on "image overhaul," signage, and the like. A small number of documents (press releases) date to the 1950s and 1970s, but the bulk are from the 1980s-1990s.
  Arrangement
  The files are arranged by topic/exhibition in rough chronological order.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  The files were compiled from various sources within N-YHS. They were found during and shortly after the institutional archives processing project of 2015-16, and added to the finding aid in 2021.
  - Working files, 1950s, 1970s-1989 (Offsite-box 10)
    Holds a few items from the 1950s and from the 1970s. Bulk of the box dates from the 1980s and primarily relates to exhibitions. There is a "recommended public relations strategic plan" from Brown Boxenbaum (January 1987).
  - Working files, 1989-1991 (Offsite-box 11)
    The box holds primarily files concerning exhibitions and other programs, with some files related to general public relations activities and notes on "image overhaul," signage, and the like.